-==www.RagBear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案集  第2季第4集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=-
校对: ptrpan
萨顿
Sutton,
萨顿 救我
Sutton help me.
救我啊 萨顿
Help me Sutton.
快救我!
Please help,
救命
help,
救我啊萨顿
help me Sutton.
萨顿 救命
Sutton help.
不要让他们带走我 萨顿
Don't let them take me Sutton.
救我啊 萨顿
Help me Sutton,
萨顿
Sutton.
不要让他们带走我啊 萨顿
Don't let them take me Sutton.
救我
Help me.
救我啊萨顿
Help me Sutton.
萨顿 救我啊
Sutton help.
快点救我啊
Please help,
救命啊!
help!
救我啊!
Help me!
快救我啊萨顿!
Help me Sutton!
萨顿
Sutton,
萨顿 萨顿 救我啊
Sutton, Sutton help,
救我啊!
help me!
萨顿
Sutton,
萨顿!
Sutton!
住院的病人
The Resident Patient
放松点 福尔摩斯
Mustn't take it so badly Holmes.
什么?
What?
我知道这么说有点难为情
Well I know it's inconvenient but you really mustn't
但你不能让它影响你的
let it affect you like this.
你在说什么啊?
Whatever do you mean?
你一直怒愤难抑
You are sitting there boiling with indignation
因为你被迫离开
because you have been forced to leave
221B这么一间舒适的公寓
the warmth and comfort of 221B by the order
哈德森太太正在进行春季大扫除
of Mrs. Hudson's spring cleaning.
我亲爱的华生 你是怎么推断出的?
My dear Watson however did you deduce that?
只是简单地运用了下你的方法罢了
By simply applying your methods Holmes.
是么?
Indeed?
相信你来这里
You'll agree that you are not here
不是为了剪发或刮胡
for either a shave or a haircut.
这是事实
That is true.
你怎么知道的呢?
How did you know?
因为很明显你自己已经刮了胡子
Because you invariably shave yourself and you are patently
而距你下一次剪发还有两周的时间
not due for a haircut for another two weeks.
正确
Correct.
你刚才很匆忙地离开了房间
And you left our rooms in some haste.
你没有戴手套 也没有拿手杖
You are without either your gloves or your cane.
继续
Go on.
嗯 我知道哈德森太太一直在
Well, I know that Mrs. Hudson's been trying to complete
忙活着春季大扫除
her spring cleaning all day.
现如今 你静坐于此
Now, you have been sitting there
双眉紧锁 闭目不语
frowning, eyes tightly closed,
咬牙切齿
grinding your teeth,
一直击打着手指
and all the time your fingers
就像活塞运动一样有规律地
have been drumming like pistons
击打着椅子扶手
on the arm of that chair.
愚钝如我也不难推断出
So given all this at once even I cannot fail to deduce
你和我们善良的管家吵架了
that you are have quarreled with our good housekeeper
然后就来理发店寻找安宁
and sought refuge in the sanity of the barbershop.
无可否认 我的推断是正确的
You cannot deny that I am right.
噢 华生 这样你就
Oh, Watson you could not be
大错特错了
further from the truth.
我是来征询理发师的意见的
I am here to get our good barber's advice
这个是在案发现场找到的头发样本
as to the specimen of hair found at the scene
是上周二在德布福特发生的血腥惨剧
of a bloody misadventure last Tuesday in Debford.
噢 快点说吧 福尔摩斯
Oh, come along Holmes.
你肯定是在担心什么的
You're worried about something.
你口中所说的焦虑
What you perceived as agitation
实际上是平静的享受才是
was indeed most intense tranquil enjoyment.
我双目紧闭是因为
My eyes were closed because I was trying to recall
昨夜演奏会上的盛况
as vividly as I could the concert
如此让人回味
that we attended last night.
你在咬牙切齿
You were grinding your teeth.
那是因为我在回想
That is because I made a slight error
厄尔吉安弹奏贝多芬的小提琴协奏曲
in my recollection of Urkian's fingering
第三章的华彩部分时
his cadenza in the third movement
出了一点小小的差错
of the Beethoven Violin Concerto
不过话说回头
Nevertheless there is an element of truth
你所说的还是有点道理的
in what you say.
啊
Ah.
一个医生
A doctor's,
一位全科医生 我想
a general practitioner's I perceive,
开业不久 或许生意还不错
not been long in practice or had much to do,
他是来找我们商量事情的
come to consult us I fancy.
我们回来得太巧了
Lucky we came back.
啊 福尔摩斯先生
Ah, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢 哈德森夫人
Thank you Mrs. Hudson.
医生 这是我的朋友兼同事 华生先生
Doctor, this is my friend and colleague Dr. Watson.
请坐 阁下莅临寒舍 未知所为何事
Pray resume your seat and tell me how I may serve you.
我的确是医生 我叫珀西・特里维廉
Well, I am indeed a doctor and my name is Percy Travelian
住在布鲁克街403号
and I live at number 403 Brook Street.
你不就是
Aren't you the author
《原因不明的神经损伤》
of a monograph upon obscure nervous lesions?
那篇论文的作者吗?
是的 但甚少听人提及
Yes, but I so seldom hear of the work
我还以为早被遗忘了呢
I thought it quite dead.
怎么会呢
By no means.
出版商向我说
My publishers have given me
这本书销路不广
a most discouraging account of its sales.
你也是从医的吗?
You are yourself a medical man?
退役的外科军医
Retired army surgeon.
我对神经病学很感兴趣
My hobby has always been the study of nervous disease.
我很希望能够对它
I should of course like to make it
进行专门研究 不过 一个人
an absolute specialty but a man
当然必须从事他首先能够着手的工作
must take what he can get first.
显然 这是题外话了
However, this is beside the question
福尔摩斯先生 我知道
and I do appreciate, Mr. Holmes,
你的时间是多么宝贵
how very valuable your time is.
在布鲁克街我的寓所里
The fact is that a singular train of events
最近发生了一连串非常奇怪的事情
has occurred recently at my house in Brook Street
今晚 这些事情已经到了非常严重的关头
and tonight they came to such a head
我感到实在不能再耽误了
that I felt it was impossible to wait another hour
必须马上来请你出出主意 帮个忙
before asking for your advice and your assistance.
你要我出主意 帮忙 我非常欢迎
You are very welcome to both.
请把那些使你感到不安的事情
Let me have a detailed account of the circumstances
详细地讲给我听听
which have disturbed you.
其中有一两件事如此琐碎
Well one or two of them are so trivial
以至于我都不好意思提及
that I am almost ashamed to mention them.
不过这件事令人非常莫名片妙
But the matter is so inexplicable
而近来变得更加复杂
and the recent turn it has taken so elaborate
我只好把一切都摆在你面前
that I shall lay it all before you and you shall judge
请你取其精华 去其糟粕
what is essential and what is not.
我是伦敦大学毕业的
I am a London University man and I am not unduly
可以说我是优等生 绝不是自吹自擂
singing my praises when I say I was a very promising student
我的前途
And it was thought a distinguished career
一片光明
lay before me.
然而 就在此时 最大的障碍出现了
However, there was one great stumbling block.
钱?
Money?
是的 医生 钱
Indeed doctor, money.
我需要一笔资金开始行医
I needed capital not only to practice
以及逃离我被迫租下的
but also to get out of the scrawled rooms
一团糟的公寓
I was forced to rent.
要连像样点的设备都没有
I could not expect my patients to trust me
又怎么能叫我的病人相信我呢
if I could not afford the proper equipment.
是啊 这已经是司空见惯了
Yes, I've seen it happen to too many of us.
我也被迫从军
I myself was obliged to go into the army
以此来开始我的职业
in order to follow my career.
是啊
Indeed.
我想过放弃自己的职业
I had thought of abandoning my own career
但是突如其来的一件事改变了我的主意
except for one sudden and unexpected incident.
到底是怎样的事呢?
Exactly what kind of incident?
两年前的一个早上
One morning two years ago
一个男人上门造访 他的名字叫布莱星顿
I received a visit from a man by the name of Blessington
在此之前我们素未谋面
who until that time had been a complete stranger to me.
请进
Come in.
老天爷啊 你就住这 就这里?
Good heavens, do you live here, in this?
是的 恐怕如此
Yes, I'm afraid I do.
你就是那位
You are the same Percy Travelian
取得卓越成就
who's had so distinguished a career,
最近获奖的珀西・特里维廉先生吗?
recently won the Slater award for medicine?
正是
I am.
请坦率地回答我的问题
Then answer me frankly sir,
你会看到这样做对你是有好处的
and you'll find it in your interest to do so.
要不是你现在的财务困难
Despite your present financial situation,
你的才学一定
you clearly have all the cleverness
会让你青云直上的
that makes a successful man.
但你够圆滑机智吗?
But have you the tact?
我相信我会尽力而为的
I trust that I have my share, sir.
有无不良嗜好?
Any bad habits?
不酗酒吗?
Not drawn toward drink?
不 先生!
Now really sir.
很好 很好
Quite right, quite right.
不过我必须问一下
But I was bound to ask.
为什么呢?
Why?
为什么啊?
Why sir?
你既然有这些本事
Simply why with all these qualities
为什么不开业行医呢?
are you not in practice?
现在知道了英雄
Come now it's that old story more in the brains
为什么也要为五斗米折腰了吧?
than in the pocket hey?
要是我帮你在布鲁克街开业
Now sir what would say sir
你的意见如何?
if I were to start you in Brook Street?
专业人士要想成功必须志向高远
If a specialist is to succeed he must aim high
在布鲁克街行医只是个开始
and a practice in Brook Street is just the beginning.
留意了 要穿着光鲜
Capital, keep yourself in style,
租个像样的马车
the hire of respectable carriage and horse,
最好的手术室 候诊室和仆役
surgery that's worthy of you, waiting room, servants
还有外面能买到的最好的设备
and the best equipment that money can buy.
这些是你将会拥有的
That is what you will have sir.
但是为什么啊?
But why?
这正像别的投机事业一样
It's just like any other investment,
不过比较更保险一些
safer than most.
那么 我该做些什么事呢?
And what am I to do?
我自然会告诉你的
I'll tell you.
我要替你租房子 置家具
I will take the house, furnish it,
雇女仆 管理一切
pay the maids and run the whole place.
你所要做的就是安安分分地
All you have to do is to wear out the chair
坐在你的诊室里
in your consulting room.
你所赚的
Then you hand over to me
我要占四分之三
three quarters of everything you earn
剩下的四分之一你自己留着
and keep one quarter for yourself.
你觉得这个提议怎样呢?
Now what do you say to that sir?
你同意吗?
Do you agree?
福尔摩斯先生 这就是那个
This then Mr. Holmes was the strange proposal
叫布莱星顿的陌生人给我提的奇怪建议
with which Mr. Blessington approached me.
我不再叙述我们怎样
I will not weary you with how we
协商 成交的事
bargained and negotiated.
结果是 我在报喜节
But it ended with my moving into the house next quarter
搬进了这个寓所 并按他所提出的条件
and starting in practice on very much the same conditions
开始营业
as he had suggested.
这就是候诊室
Waiting room for your patients.
你的诊室
Your consulting room.
难以置信啊 布莱星顿先生
I can't believe it Mr. Blessington,
叫我怎么感谢你呢
nor can I thank you enough.
他把一楼最好的两间房改成了
He turned the two best rooms on the first floor
起居室和他自己的卧室
into a sitting room and a bedroom for himself
然后以住院病人的身份
and came to live with me in the character of
和我住在了一起
a resident patient.
他的心脏衰弱 但算不上不正常
His heart was weak but not abnormal.
显然 他需要经常治疗
And yet he demanded constant medical supervision.
他脾气古怪 闭门谢客
He was a man of singular habits, shunning company
深居简出 不过有一件事除外
and very seldom going out except in one respect.
在每天晚上的同一时刻 他都会
Every evening at the same time he would go for a walk
外出散步半小时 风雨不改
for half an hour exactly no matter what the weather.
而且每晚同一时刻
And every evening at the same hour
他都会踱进我的诊室
he would walk into the consulting room.
检查账目
He would then examine the books,
赚的诊费 每1畿尼他给我留5先令3便士
put down five crumpets for every guinea I had earned
其余的他全部拿走
and then carried the rest off to the strong box
放到他自己屋内的保险箱里
in his own room.
我可以非常自信地说
I may say with confidence Mr. Holmes
对这项投机生意 他永远也不会后悔
that he never had occasion to regret his speculation.
一开始 生意就很成功
From the first it was a success
近两年来 我使他变成了一个富翁
and during the last two years I have made him a rich man.
就是这些了 福尔摩斯先生
So much Mr. Holmes,
我过去的经历以及
for my past history and my relations
和布莱星顿先生的关系
with the resident patient Mr. Blessington.
我要告诉你的 现在只剩下一个问题
It only remains for me now to tell you
就是我今晚来此求教的原因
what has occurred to bring me here tonight.
几星期之前 布莱星顿先生下楼来找我
Some weeks ago Mr. Blessington came down to me
我似乎觉得
in as it seemed to me
他的心情异常激动      特里维廉医生
a considerable state of agitation.        Dr. Travelian,
特里维廉医生 特里维廉医生
Dr. Travelian, Dr. Travelian,
Dr. Travelian, Dr. Travelian sir.
布莱星顿先生 冷静下
Mr. Blessington calm yourself sir.
冷静 你叫我怎么冷静?
Calm myself? Calm myself?
你没有听说那件盗窃案吗?
But my dear sir have you not heard of the burglary?
盗窃案?
Burglary?
哪里啊?
Where?
不 不 不 不是这里 先生
No, no, no not here sir,
不是这里 但是可能会的
not here, but it could have been.
可能会的...
Could have been...
一周之内整栋房子
Within a week the whole house had become
的门窗都被加固闩牢
a fortress of bolts and bars and locks.
你确定这些栅栏足够坚固吗?
Are you sure these bars are strong enough?
它们坚固得用在英格兰银行都绰绰有余了
They'd be strong enough for the bank of England, sir.
布莱星顿先生?
Mr. Blessington?
当我向他问到这件事时
When I questioned him upon the point
他变得非常无礼 于是我
he became so offensive that I was compelled
就不再谈这件事了
to drop the subject.
刚开始我还以为他
At first Mr. Holmes I thought he merely sought
只是想保护他的保险箱
to protect his strong box,
但后来我发觉
but then I suspected that it was his life
他是在保护自己的性命
he was protecting.
从那之后他就完全不外出了
From then on he stopped going out all together,
不停地从窗户往外看
peered continually out of his windows
把自己锁在房间里
and kept himself locked in his room in what
我只能说他已经到了极度焦虑的状态
I could only describe as a state of mortal dread.
特里维廉医生 在你继续之前
Dr. Travelian, before you continue,
你说你发现布莱星顿先生
you say you found this man Blessington
终日卧床 手抓报纸 并且日渐虚弱?
prostrate on his bed clutching a newspaper?
准确点说是
More precisely the remains of a newspaper
他撕下的报纸条
for he had torn it to shreds.
撕成报纸条
Torn to shreds.
你还记得报纸上的内容吗?
Do you recall the contents of this newspaper at all?
不记得了 但我发现了些新的情况
No, I'm afraid not even if I'd known what I was looking for.
什么时候呢?
When was this?
几周之前
It was some weeks ago,
好像是五月初
the beginning of May I think.
时间一天天过去
Gradually as time passed
他的恐惧似乎逐渐消失了
his fears appeared to die away
他又恢复了常态
and he renewed his former habits.
晚安 特里维廉医生
Good evening Dr. Travelian.
外面天气多好啊
Wonderful evening outside.
我又开始出去散步了
I'm beginning to enjoy my walks again.
然后突如其来地一件事
And then suddenly a fresh event reduced him
让他就此卧床不起
to the pitiable state of prostration
知道现在
in which he now lies.
事情是这样的 昨天我收到一封信
What happened was yesterday I received this letter
一位侨居在英国的俄罗斯贵族寄来的
from a Russian nobleman now resident in England
他深受强直性昏厥病的折磨
who suffers from catalepsy.
他在信中写道亟愿到我处就医
In it he announces his intention of visiting me
准备明晚六点一刻左右
for a consultation this very evening
前往就诊
at a quarter past six.
由于对强直症进行研究的主要困难
Because of the chief difficulty in the study of catalepsy
在于这种疾病是罕见的
and the rareness of the disease
你可以相信 在约定时间那时
you may believe that at the appointed hour
我已经心焦地等候在我的诊室里
I was eager to receive the patient.
晚上好啊 先生
Good evening gentlemen.
我是特里维廉医生 我想
I'm Dr. Travelian and it was you sir
就是阁下给我写的信吧?
I assume who wrote to me?
医生 我的父亲很少说英语的
My father speaks very little English doctor,
所以希望你不介意我陪他进来
so I trust you will excuse my coming in with him
他的健康问题
as his health is a matter
对我是极重要的事情
of the most overwhelming importance to me.
是的 这个我清楚 先生
Yes, I respect that sir.
芬顿
Fenton,
或许在诊治时 你愿意留在诊室里吧?
perhaps you would like to join us for the consultation?
不行 绝对不行
Nyet, nyet, not for all of the world.
我受不了这种痛苦
It is more painful to me than I can express.
如果我看到我父亲
If I were to see my father in one of those
疾病发作时那种可怕的样子
dreadful seizures I am convinced
我相信我是忍受不了的
I would never survive it.
我自己的神经官能
My own nervous system
也十分敏感
is an exceptionally sensitive one.
你如允许
With your permission I will remain
在你给我父亲诊治时
in your waiting room while you go into my father's case.
我可以在候诊室里等候
好的 当然可以啦
Yes, of course.
谢谢 医生
thank you doctor.
谢谢你 芬顿
Thank you Fenton.
现在先生 请允许我
Now sir, I hope you will forgive me
问你几个基本的问题
if I ask you a few basic questions.
首先 你能告诉我你的年龄吗?
First, can you tell me your age?
Sixty-seven.
除了强直性昏厥病
And apart from catalepsy
你是否觉得自己身体健壮呢?
would you say you are physically sound?
也就是说你的身体还好吗?
Normally do you have good health?
嗯 没有头痛?
Um, no headaches?
腹痛呢?
Abdominal pain?
有没有感觉到疼痛?
Any pain at all?
没有
No.
很好
Good.
首先我要给你做个全身检查
Naturally I will examine you thoroughly
但这只是初步检查
but this is merely a preliminary.
你抽雪茄吗?
Do you smoke cigars?
是的
Yes.
你喝酒吗?
Do you drink alcohol?
伏特加
Vodka.
伏特加?
Vodka?
我知道了
I see.
每天?
Every day?
我没想到...
I didn't expect...
我最初的感觉是既怜悯又害怕
my first feeling was one of pity and horror.
后来 我的职业兴趣
My second I fear was rather
占了上风
one of professional satisfaction.
哪一方面都没有发现与我以前所诊断的
There was nothing markedly abnormal in his condition
这种病例有不一致的现象
which had harmonized with my former experiences.
在之前类似的病例中 我使用
I had obtained good results in such cases.
烷基亚硝酸吸入剂 取得了良好的疗效
By the inhalation of nitrite of alma
现在似乎正是试验
and the present seemed an admirable opportunity
它疗效的极好机会
of testing its virtues.
先生 我相信你能听见我
Now sir, I believe you can hear me.
我很快就会回来
I should be back directly rest assured.
芬顿
Fenton,
芬顿 芬顿 过来
Fenton, Fenton immediately.
芬顿 你15分钟之前
Fenton, the two gentlemen you showed in
带上来那两位先生
less than 15 minutes ago,
你见到他们走了吗?
did you see them leave?
走? 没有啊 先生
Leave, no sir.
你确定?
Are you sure?
我确定 先生
I'm positive sir.
晚上好啊 特里维廉医生
Good evening Dr. Travelian.
晚上好 布莱星顿先生
Good evening Mr. Blessington
你今天的散步如何呢?
and how was your walk today?
有点小雨 但还是很愉快的
A little rain but very amiable my good sir.
非常愉快
Very amiable.
你听到他们离开吗?
Did you hear them leave?
没有 先生
No, sir.
我不在大厅附近
I was nowhere near the hall.
你不应该离开的
Well you should have been.
这是你的职责
That is your duty.
我知道你是刚来的 但现在你应该记住了
Now I know you are new here but you should know by now.
医生 医生!
Doctor! doctor!
doctor! doctor!
有人进过我的房间
Someone has been in my room.
没有人进过你的房间 先生
No one has been in your room sir.
说谎
A lie.
你在说谎
You're lying to me.
我向你保证我没有
I assure you I am not.
芬顿 你进过布莱星顿先生的房间吗?
Fenton, have you been in Mr. Blessington's room?
我肯定没有
Of course I haven't.
我就说 你听到了吧
There you are you see.
你自己上来看下吧
Then come up and see for yourself.
什么事 先生
Now sir.
看下那里吧
Look at those.
你敢说这是我的脚印?
Are you telling me that they're mine?
嗯 一眼看上去
Well at first glance they do appear
这的确大了点 不是你的
to be too large for you.
这些肯定不是我的脚印
Of course they're not mine.
我从来都是在前门脱套鞋的
I always remove my galoshes at the front door.
有什么被盗的吗?
Has anything been stolen?
没有 但这个不是重点
No, but that's not the point.
没有东西被盗?
Nothing has been stolen?
我的隐私被陌生人侵犯了
My privacy has been invaded by a stranger,
这还不够吗?
is that not enough?
布莱星顿先生?
Mr. Blessington?
你给我出去 我要单独呆会 出去
Leave me alone, go away and leave me alone.
我相信我能帮上什么忙的
Surely there's something I can do to help.
要我叫警察吗?
Shall I call the police?
不要 不要叫那些喇叭手
No... Not those buglers.
现在只有一个人能帮我的
There's only one person who can help me now.
这就是我上这儿来的原因了
And that is why I am here.
这么琐碎的事情麻烦你 我实在很抱歉
But I must apologize for such a trivial reason.
一个什么都不偷的贼
A thief that doesn't steal.
他有指名道姓说要我帮忙吗?
Did he ask for me by name?
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
那我们走吧
Then let us be on our way.
谢谢
Thank you.
这边?
This way?
站在那里
Stay where you are.
我有手枪的 我保证
I have a pistol and I give you my word
要是你再走近一点 我就射你
I will shoot if you come any nearer.
布莱星顿先生 不要那么无礼!
Mr. Blessington this is outrageous sir!
你不认得我吗?
Do you not recognize me?
是你吗 医生?
Is that you doctor?
是的 就是我啊
Yes, of course it is me.
另外两位先生
The other two gentlemen,
他们是假扮的吗?
are they what they pretend to be?
他们是夏洛克・福尔摩斯先生
They are Mr. Sherlock Holmes
和他的朋友华生医生
and his friend Dr. Watson.
上帝啊 布莱星顿先生
Good God Mr. Blessington,
是你让我叫他们来的
it was you that asked me to fetch them.
是的 是的 是的 请原谅我
Yes, yes, yes, forgive me,
原谅我
forgive me.
先生们 上来吧
Gentlemen do come up.
我的警惕冒犯到你们的话 我很抱歉
I'm sorry if my precautions have annoyed you.
晚上好 福尔摩斯先生
Good evening Mr. Holmes.
我相信我是到了迫不得已的地步
I'm sure I'm very much obliged
才请你们来的
to you for coming around.
没人比我更需要你的建议了 先生
No one has ever needed your advice more than I, no one.
我相信特里维廉医生已经告诉你
I expect Dr. Travelian has told you
有人不经允许闯进我的房间这件事了
of this unwarrantable intrusion into my rooms.
布莱星顿先生
My sir, Mr. Blessington,
那两个男人是谁呢?
who are these two men?
哪两个男人啊 我不认识他们
Which two men, I don't know them.
那他们为什么要打扰你呢?
Then why do they wish to molest you?
打扰我?
Molest me?
你可不能指望我来回答这个问题
You could hardly expect me to answer that.
你是说你不知道?
You mean that you don't know?
请进
Come in here, please.
请进来吧!
Just have the kindness to step in here!
我从来就不是个富人 福尔摩斯先生
I've never been a rich man, Mr. Holmes.
我一生只做过一次投资
I've never made but one investment in my life,
特里维廉医生会告诉你
Dr. Travelian will tell you that
我有多么不相信银行家的
but I don't believe in bankers sir.
绝对不要相信银行家
Never trust a banker
福尔摩斯先生 绝不!
Mr. Holmes, never.
这是我们之间的秘密
It's between ourselves.
我全部身家都在这保险箱里
What little I have is here in this strong box.
现在你知道
So you can understand what it means to me
陌生人
when unknown people
潜进我的房间这件事对我有多重要了吧
force themselves into my rooms.
布莱星顿先生 要是你一定要蒙骗我的话
Mr. Blessington I cannot possibly advise you
我是没法帮助你的
if you try to deceive me.
蒙骗你?
Deceive you?
我已经告诉你一切了
But I've told you everything.
晚安 特里维廉医生
Good night Dr. Travelian.
福尔摩斯先生 你不给我一些指教吗?
Mr. Holmes, no advice for me?
我对你的指教就是请讲真话
My advice to you is to speak the truth.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
马车!
Cab!
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我能从那人的眼睛中看出
I can read in a man's eyes
他只是害怕自己的幻想
when it's his own skin that he's frightened of.
是的 但你为什么说他说谎呢?
Yes, But why did you call him a liar?
因为我知道他认识那两个人
Because I am certain that he does know who these men are.
马车!
Cab!
一位俄罗斯年轻人
A young Russian
潜进布莱星顿先生的房间
penetrated to Blessington's rooms
他的同谋就引开医生的注意力
while his confederate kept the doctor from interfering.
强直性昏厥病是很好模仿的
And of course catalepsy is a very easy complaint to imitate.
是的 我知道 我自己也做过
Yes, I know I've done it myself.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
会不会有这么一个可能性
Might there be one alternative,
十分荒诞但同时也是可信的
grotesquely improbably no doubt but still just conceivable,
整个故事就是患了强直性昏厥的人
might the whole story of the cataleptic Russian
和那个儿子都是特里维廉医生编出来的
and son be a concoction of Dr. Travelian
他自己居心不良闯进布莱星顿先生的房间
who for his own purposes has been in Blessington's room?
但你看到楼梯上地毯上的脚印了吗?
But did you see the footprints on the stair carpet?
那鞋印是方头的 而布莱星顿先生的
They were square toed, quite unlike Blessington's
鞋子是圆头的 同时又比特里维廉医生的
which are round and an inch and a third longer
长了1.3寸
than Dr. Travelians.
我觉得我们今晚要好好想下
I think we can sleep on this Watson
不出所料的话
but I should be surprised if we do not hear
他们明早就会来找我们的
from Brook Street in the morning.
晚安
Good night.
晚安 老朋友
Night old fellow.
早啊 医生
Morning doctor.
你的茶放门外了
Your tea is here.
谢谢 诺拉
Thank you Nora.
布莱星顿先生 你的茶
Mr. Blessington, your breakfast tea.
布莱星顿先生?
Mr. Blessington?
华生...
Watson...
赶快穿衣服
get dressed quickly.
马车在等我们了
There's a cab waiting for us.
为什么啊?
Why?
什么事啊?
What's the matter?
布鲁克街那件事
The Brook Street business.
有什么新消息吗?
Any fresh news?
看在上帝的面上
For God's sake,
立即前来 珀西・特里维廉
come at once, P. Travelian.
噢 福尔摩斯先生 很高兴你能来
Oh, Mr. Holmes I'm so glad you could come.
发生什么事了?
What has happened?
布莱星顿先生自杀了
Mr. Blessington has committed suicide.
自杀?
Suicide?
是的
Yes.
他在夜里上吊了
He hung himself during the night.
有人碰过尸体吗?
Has the body been touched?
没有
No.
听差呢?
Where's the page?
找不到
Nowhere to be found.
早上好啊 巡官
Good morning inspector.
福尔摩斯先生 很高兴见到你
Mr. Holmes, delighted to see you.
现在请你看下
Now please take a look.
我们正准备把他放下来
We were just about to take him down.
是的 巡官
Right, inspector.
担架
Stretcher.
就这样了
That'll be all.
你听说过案子发生前的一些情况了吗?
Have heard of the events leading up to this affair?
是的 特里维廉医生已经跟我说过一些了
Yes, Dr. Travelian has told me something of them.
你有什么意见吗?
And have you formed an opinion?
目前就我所知 他
Now as far as I can see, the man was driven
应该是被吓疯了
out of his senses by fright.
在这张床上他睡了好一阵子
The bed has been well slept in.
有很深的压痕
There was his impression deep enough for all to see.
你也知道 自杀常常发生
It is about 5:00 in the morning.
在早晨五点钟左右
You know that suicides are most common.
这大约也就是他上吊的时间了
That would be about the time that he hanged himself.
看来 他是经过再三考虑才这样做的
It seems to be a very deliberate affair.
根据肌肉僵硬的情况判断
Yes, from the rigidity of the limbs
我看他已经死了大约三个小时
I'd say he'd been dead about three hours.
谢谢华生.
Thank you Watson.
你注意到屋子里有什么异常现象吗?
Notice anything peculiar about the room.
在洗手池上发现
There was a screwdriver on the mantel piece
一把螺丝起子和一些螺丝钉
还发现他夜里似乎抽过不少烟
and he seems to have smoked heavily during the night.
这是我在壁炉里找到的
I found these in the fireplace.
你找到他的雪茄烟嘴了吗?
Have you his cigar holder?
没有 我没有看到
No, I haven't seen one.
那么 他的烟盒呢?
His cigar case then?
有 在他的外衣口袋里
Yes, it was in his coat pocket.
这是一支哈瓦那烟
This is savannah,
而壁炉台上的这些是特殊品种
And these others are the cigars of a peculiar sort
是荷兰从
which is imported by the Dutch
它的东印度殖民地进口的
from the East Indian colonies.
这些雪茄通常都包着稻草
They're usually wrapped in straw you know and are thinner
并且比别的牌子的都细
for their length than any other brand.
我相信你没有读过
I don't suppose you've read monograph
雪茄和抽雪茄这个行为的论文
on cigars and cigar action?
我 嗯...
Well I, um...
没有 当然没有 谢谢
No, of course not. Thank you.
这些是用烟嘴抽的 而这些不是
These have been smoked with a holder and these without.
这些是用一把较钝的小刀削过的
These have been cut by a not very sharp knife
另两个烟头是
and these have had their ends bitten off
用尖锐的牙齿咬下来的
by a set of very excellent teeth.
昨晚这里有三个人
There were three men here last night.
老天啊 可是什么都没有被盗
Good heavens but nothing was stolen
他们究竟在干吗?
so what were they doing here?
这是我们要找出的
That is what we have to find out.
他们怎么进来的?
How did they get in?
像我们一样从前门进来的
The same way we did through the front door.
早晨门是上锁的
But the door was barred in the morning.
那么门是在他们走后锁上的
Then it was barred after they left.
你怎么知道呢?
Well how do you know that?
我看到了他们留下的痕迹
I saw their traces.
请稍等一等
If you would just give me a few moments Inspector,
我就能给你们进一步说明它的情况
I may be able to give you some further information.
不要动 华生
Don't move Watson.
事实很简单
The actual facts are very simple.
如无意外下午
And I shall be surprised if by the afternoon
我就能给你和他们一个交代
I cannot give you the reasons for them as well.
但是 福尔摩斯 你现在不能说吗?
But Holmes, can't you tell us anything now?
噢 事情的次序可是不能颠倒的
Oh, there is no doubt as to the sequence of events.
有三个人
The three of them in it.
一个年轻人 一个老人
A young man, an old man
还有另外一个人身份不明
and a third to whose identity I have no clue.
头两个不用想就知道
The first two I need hardly remark are the same
是假扮成俄罗斯父子的那两个
who masqueraded as the Russian Count and his son.
因此我们很清楚他们的特征
So we can give a very good description of them,
是吧 特里维廉医生
can we not Dr. Travelian?
他们是被这所房子里的
They were admitted by a confederate
一个同伙放进来的
inside the house.
他们进到大厅
They entered the hall.
首先是老人 然后是年轻人
The older man first, the younger man second
神秘人在后面
and the unknown man in the rear.
他们上楼梯
They ascended the stairs.
他们用一根铁丝去转动里面的钥匙
With the help of a wire they forced the key.
你们甚至不用放大镜 也可以从
Even without the lens you can see where
这把钥匙榫槽上的划痕看出
the pressure has been applied.
他们进入室内 第一步
On entering the room the first proceeding
一定是把布莱星顿先生的嘴给塞住
must have been to gag Mr. Blessington.
很明显 他们把他安置妥当以后
Having secured Blessington it is evident to me
就商量了一番
that a consultation of some sort was held
这种商量可能具有起诉的性质
probably in the nature of a judicial proceeding.
它一定进行了相当一段时间
It must have lasted for some time
因为正是在这段时间
for it was then
他们吸了这几支雪茄
that the cigars were smoked.
老人坐在那张
It was there that the older man sat
柳条椅子上
in the wicker chair.
是他用的雪茄烟嘴
It was he who used the cigar holder.
年轻人坐那里
The younger man sat there.
他把烟灰磕在了衣柜的对面
He knocked his ash off against the chest of drawers.
第三个人在室内踱来踱去
The unknown fellow paced up and down.
我想 这时布莱星顿正笔直地坐在床上
Blessington I think sat upright in the bed,
不过对这一点我还不能绝对肯定
but of that I cannot be absolutely certain.
最后 他们就去抓布莱星顿...
It ended of course by them taking Blessington...
这是他们早就安排好了的
Now this matter was so prearranged
因为我相信他们随身带来了
that it is my belief that they brought with them
某种滑轮用作绞刑架
some sort of block or pulley to serve as a gallows.
噢 是的 绞刑架 巡官
Oh, yes as gallows Inspector.
这是种报仇的仪式
This was a revenge ritual.
这故事多精彩啊
Well an extraordinary story.
但有什么证据呢?
But what proof?
天黑之前我会给你证据的
I'll have it before the day is out.
你还没解释
You haven't explained about
螺丝起子和螺丝的用处呢
the screws and the screwdriver.
那是用来固定滑轮组或者滑轮的
Oh, that was to fix up the block or pulley.
但他们看到吊灯钩的时候
But when they saw the chandelier hook
很自然地他们就就地取材
they naturally saved themselves the trouble.
如果我可以向你进一句忠言的话 警长
No Inspector I suggest that you immediately make inquiries
那就应当逮捕那个小听差
about the page and arrest him.
这是肯定的 福尔摩斯先生
Certainly Mr. Holmes.
我在三点钟之前回来
I will be back here a little before 3:00.
再见
Good day.
我想哈德森夫人看到这个的话
I daresay Mrs. Hudson will be a little put out
肯定会很不开心
when she sees all this.
你在找什么?
What are you looking for?
沃辛顿 W
Worthington, W,
沃辛顿 三月 1880 我确定
Worthingon, March 1880 I'm sure.
三月 80
March '80,
'80,
一月
January,
二月
February,
三月
March.
是这个吗?
Any good?
华生...
Watson...
布莱星顿 或者说 那时候的萨顿
Blessington or Sutton as he was known then.
哈德森夫人
Mrs. Hudson.
你的小船很快就来了 医生
Your little boat is coming along beautifully Doctor.
噢 谢谢啊 哈德森夫人
Oh, thank you Mrs. Hudson.
我要走了
I must run.
啊 谢谢
Ah, thank you.
特里维廉医生
Dr. Travelian.
有什么消息吗 警官?
Any news Inspector?
是的 先生 我们在
Yes, sir we've got the page
两条街外找到听差在喝酒
drinking his earnings two streets away.
我抓到他们了      你抓到他们啦?
But I got the man.        You've got them?
至少我知道他们的身份了
Or at least I've got their identity.
抢劫沃辛顿银行的那一伙?
The Worthington Bank Gang?
的确
Precisely.
那布莱星顿肯定就是萨顿了
Well then Blessington must have been Sutton.
正确
Exactly.
那现在就水落石出了
Well that makes it clear as crystal.
我还不懂呢
not to me I'm afraid.
华生医生 你 呃...
Dr. Watson would you, uh...
你应该听说过
You may have heard of the great
沃辛顿银行劫案吧?
Worthington bank affair?
一共有5个人
There were five men in it.
三个昨晚出现在这里
The three who were in this room,
还有两个叫卡特莱特和布莱星顿
a fourth named Cartwright and Blessington.
是的 我们走吧
Alright, let's be gone.
这可是要被判死刑的
It's a hanging job now.
没人知道就不是啦
Only if someone squeals.
就是他了
That's him.
你确定?
Are you positive?
是的 就是他了
Oh, yes, that's him.
萨顿 萨顿 你死定了 死定了 死定了
Sutton, Sutton, you're dead, dead, dead.
萨顿 你死定了
Sutton, you're dead.
萨顿...
Sutton...
不用担心 萨顿先生 他会被判死刑的
Don't worry Mr. Sutton, it's a hanging job now.
萨顿 你听着
Sutton, you hear.
萨顿 或者说 布莱星顿
Sutton or Blessington
成了污点证人
who was the worst of the gang turned informer.
由于他的证词 卡特莱特被绞死
On his evidence Cartright was hanged
另外三个人被判入狱15年
and the other three got 15 years apiece.
比德尔 海沃德和莫法特
Bibel, Haywood and Moffit
几周之前出狱了
were released from prison just a few weeks ago
他们被提前释放
which was several years before their full term.
他们出来的消息让布莱星顿
It was news of their release which caused Blessington
惊慌不已 他加固了房子
to panic and have this house secured.
这么说他害怕的不是盗窃案?
So it was not the fear burglary that had frightened him?
不 不 那只是个烟雾弹
No, no, that was a mere blind.
那么在我身上投资
And so setting me up in practice
也是想巧妙地保护他自己?
was an elaborate charade to protect himself.
可是他为什么不把这件事告诉你呢?
Well why could he not tell you this?
他在尽量
He was trying to hide his own identity
向所有人隐瞒自己的身份
from everybody for as long as he could.
他的秘密是可耻的
His secret was shameful
他不可能自己泄漏出来
and he couldn't bring himself to divulge it.
但是 他虽然卑鄙
However, wretch as he was
却依然处于英国法律的保护之下
he was still living under the shield of British law.
警长 我毫不怀疑
And I have no doubt Inspector
你可以看到
that we shall see
尽管那个盾没有起到保护作用
that though that shield may fail to guard,
那把正义的剑还是会替他复仇的
the sword of justice is still there to avenge.
尽管夏洛克・福尔摩斯十分努力
In spite of the efforts of Sherlock Holmes
那三个杀害布莱星顿的凶手
the three murderers of Blessington
骗过了警方 离开了这个国家
eluded the police and fled the country
上了一艘去葡萄牙的船
aboard a ship bound for Portugal.
几周之后我们得悉
It was a few weeks later that we learned
那艘"诺拉克列依那"号
that the ship, the Nora Crainer
和全体船员数年以前在葡萄牙海岸
had sunk with all hands upon the Portuguese Coast
距波尔图以北数十哩的地方遇难
some leagues to the north of a porter.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
什么事?
What's wrong?
嗯 我正准备用一天时间写下
Well it's just that I was going to spend the day writing
特里维廉医生的那宗案件
the case of Dr. Travelian
趁这一切我都还记得
while the facts are still fresh.
哦 你是说... 哦 我明白了
Oh, you mean... oh, I understand.
太谢谢了
Thanks awfully.
可我现在无法集中精神写作
It's just that it is difficult to concentrate otherwise.
你说什么样的题目好呢?
What will you entitle this particular account?
我不知道你对我的作品竟还有兴趣
I didn't know you were interested in my writing.
我一直都对你的标题的选择很感兴趣
I am always interested in your choice of titles.
我想我会用
Well I thought I would call it
布鲁克街疑团
the Brook Street Mystery.
不行?
No?
我自己的话 就会取名叫
Well I myself would prefer
住院的病人 但是
The Resident Patient, but please
别让我影响到你的思维
do not let me influence you.
布鲁克街疑团很不错了
The Brook Street Mystery no doubt would suffice.
00:破烂熊字幕组
-==www.RagBear.com==-
欢迎加入